The last lecture of 6.046
6.046到了尾声~~o(≧v≦)o~
We are here today to talk more about cache oblivious algorithms.
我们今天再讲讲缓存参数无关算法
Last class, we saw several cache oblivious algorithms,
上节课我们见识了几种算法
although none of them quite too difficult.
不过那些算法没什么难度
Today we will see two difficult cache oblivious algorithms,
今天我们来看看两个难一点的算法
a little bit more advanced.
这两个更高端
I figure we should do something advanced for the last class
我想既然是最后一节课 那就来点高端的东西
just to get to some exciting climax.
来个一发入魂
So without further ado, let's get started.
闲话少说 开始干活
Last time, we looked at the binary search problem.
上节课我们讲了二分法
Or, we looked at binary search, rather.
或者说 分析了二分法
And so, the binary search did not do so well
而且我们知道 二分法在缓参无关时
in the cache oblivious context.
表现得不是很好
And, some people asked me after class
下课后有些人来问我
Is it possible to do binary search well cache-obliviously
缓参无关的二分法能不能再给力点？
And, indeed it is with something called static search trees.
当然可以 我们用静态搜索树就可以做到
So, this is really binary search.
实际上 它也是二分法
So, I mean, the abstract problem is I give you N items, say presorted
说得抽象点 就是给你N个有序的元素
build some static data structure
建立某种静态的数据结构
so that you can search among those N items quickly.
使你能够快速搜索这N个元素
And quickly, I claim, means log base B of N.
我说的快速 是指以B为底的log N
We know that with B trees,
我们知道 对于B树
our goal is to get log base B of N.
我们的目标是以B为底的log N
We know that we can achieve that with B trees when we know B.
如果B是已知的 那我们已经可以做到了
We'd like to do that when we don't know B.
我们希望就算不知道B也能做到
And that's what cache oblivious static search trees achieve.
而这正是缓参无关静态搜索树能够做到的事
So here's what we're going to do.
下面是具体做法
As you might suspect, we're going to use a tree.
你们可能猜到了 我们要用一个树
So, we're going to store our N elements in a complete binary tree.
我们先把N个元素放在一个完全二叉树中
We can't use B trees because we don't know what B is.
我们用不了B树 因为B还是未知的
So, we'll use a binary tree.
那么我们就用一个二叉树
And the key is how we lay out a binary tree.
关键就是我们如何构造这个二叉树
The binary tree will have N nodes.
这个二叉树有N个节点
Or, you can put the data in the leaves.
或者你可以把数据放在叶子节点上
It doesn't really matter.
这些都不是重点
So, here's our tree.
那么这就是我们的树了
There are the N nodes.
里面有N个节点
And we're storing them,
现在 我们要存储数据
I didn't say, in order, you know,
忘了说 是有序地存储
in the usual way, in order in a binary tree,
按照一般的方法 有序存储在二叉树里
which makes it a binary search tree.
这样它就是一个二叉搜索树
So we now had a search in this thing.
这样我们就可以在树里做查找
So, the search will just start at the root
从根节点开始查找
and a walk down some root-to-leaf path.
沿某条路径直到叶子节点
OK, and each point you know whether to go left or to go right
在每个节点处 你都知道要向左走还是向右走
because things are in order.
因为这些都是有序的
So we're assuming here that we have an ordered universe of keys.
那么 我们假设这是一个有序元素的集合
So that's easy. We know that search will take log N time.
这就很明显了 我们知道搜索要花费log N的时间
The question is how many memory transfers?
问题是存储的传输量有多少？
We'd like a lot of the nodes near the root
我们想把根节点周围的许多节点
to be somehow closer to gather in one block.
都集中到一个内存块中
But we don't know what the block size is.
不过我们不知道这个块的大小
So what we are going to do is carve the tree in the middle level.
所以我们要做的是 将这颗树从中间进行分割
We're going to use divide and conquer for our layout of the tree
用分治法来设计这个树的内存布局
how we order the nodes in memory.
设计节点在内存里是分布形式
And the divide and conquer is based on cutting in the middle,
这个分治法就是把树从中间切开
which is a bit weird.
有点诡异
It's not our usual divide and conquer.
这可不是一般的分治法
And we'll see this more than once today.
但今天我们会反复提及到它
So, when you cut on the middle level,
那么 我们给中间来了一刀
if the height of your original tree is log N, roughly
如果树原本的高度是log N
maybe log N plus one or something, it's roughly log N,
或者是log N加上常数 但大致就是log N
then the top half will be log N over two.
那么 上半部分的高度就是log N/2
And at the height of the bottom pieces will be log N over two.
下半部分也是log N/2
How many nodes will there be in the top tree?
那上半部分有多少个节点？
N over two? Not quite.
N/2？ 不太对吧
Two to the log N over two, square root of N.
2的logN/2次方 解出来就是√n
OK, so it would be about root N nodes over here.
所以这里就有√n个节点
And therefore, there will be about root N subtrees down here,
因此 这下面就大约有√n个子树
one for each, or a couple for each leaf.
一个叶节点对于一个或多个子树
OK, so we have these subtrees of root N,
然后 这些子树也都有√n个节点
and there are about root N of them.
大约一共有√n个子树
OK, this is how we are carving our tree.
我们就这样把树分割开来
Now, we're going to recurse on each of the pieces.
现在 我们要递归地分割下去
I'd like to redraw this slightly, sorry,
这个图得稍微改改
just to make it a little bit clearer.
这样能更明了些
These triangles are really trees,
这些三角形都是树
and they are connected by edges to this tree up here.
它们通过一些边跟上面这棵树相连
So what we are really doing is
我们所做的就是
carving in the middle level of edges in the tree.
把树中部的这些边切断
And if N is not exactly a power of two
如果N不是2的整数幂
you have to round your level by taking floors or ceilings.
这条边的位置可能要上下浮动
But you cut roughly in the middle level of edges.
不过大体位置是在中间
There is a lot of edges here.
这里有很多条边
You conceptually slice there.
你往这里来上一刀
That gives you a top tree and the bottom tree,
树就分成了顶部树和底部树
several bottom trees, each of size roughly root N.
而底部树有很多个 它们的大小都为√N
OK, and then we are going to recursively layout
然后我们递归地分割
these root N plus one subtrees, and then concatenate.
这√N+1棵子树 然后把他们连接在一起
So, this is the idea of the recursive layout.
这就是递归分布的思想
We sought recursive layouts with matrices last time.
上一次我们是用递归分布来处理矩阵
This is doing the same thing for a tree.
这次只是将处理的对象换成了树
So, I want to recursively layout the top tree.
我现在要对顶部树进行递归分布
So here's the top tree.
这是我们的顶部树
And I imagine it being somehow squashed down
想象一下它被压扁了
into a linear array recursively.
变成了一个线性序列
And then I do the same thing for each of the bottom trees.
然后 我对这些底部树也做同样的事
So here are all the bottom trees.
这些是底部树
And I squashed each of them down into some linear order.
我把它们每个都压成线性序列
And then I concatenate those linear orders.
然后把这些线性序列都连接起来
That's the linear order of this tree.
这就是这个树的线性序列了
And you need a base case.
当然需要有一个基准情形
And the base case, just a single node,
基准情形就是只有一个节点
is stored in the only order of a single node there is.
它的线性序列就是它本身
OK, so that's a recursive layout of a binary search tree.
这就是一个二叉搜索树的递归分布
It turns out this works really well.
你会发现这很有用
And let's quickly do a little example
我们来举一些简单的例子
just so it's completely clear what this layout is
来把这种分布方式搞清楚
because it's a bit bizarre maybe the first time you see it.
因为如果你们以前没学过的话 会感觉很诡异
So let me draw my favorite picture.
画这个是我的拿手好戏
So here's a tree of height four or three depending on how you count.
树的高度是四或者三 这取决于你的计算方式
We divide in the middle level, and we say, OK, that's the top tree.
我们在树中部做分割 那么上面的就是顶部树
And then these are the bottom trees.
下面这些是底部树
So there's four bottom trees.
这里有四个底部树
So there are four children hanging off the root tree.
也就是说顶部树下面连着四个子树
They each have the same size in this case.
这里它们的大小都一样
They should all roughly be the same size.
通常它们都是差不多大的
And the first we layout the top thing
然后我们对顶部树进行分布
where we divide on the middle level.
先在中部进行分割
We say, OK, this comes first.
那好 最上面的就是1
And then, the bottom subtrees come next, two and three.
接下来底部的子树就是2和3
So, I'm writing down the order
我写的这个顺序
in which these nodes are stored in an array.
就是它们在数组里面的顺序
And then, we visit this tree so we get four, five, six.
然后我们到这个子树 得到4、5、6
And then we visit this one so we get seven, eight, nine.
然后到这个子树 得到7、8、9
And then the subtree, 10, 11, 12, and then the last subtree.
然后下一个 10、11、12 再然后是最后一个子树
So that's the order in which you store these 15 nodes.
这就是这15个节点的存储顺序
And you can build that up recursively.
你可以通过递归来进行构造
OK, so the structure is fairly simple,
这个结构其实很简单
just a binary structure which we know and love,
就是我们喜闻乐见的二分结构
but store it in this funny order.
不过存储方式很非主流
This is not depth first search order or level order,
这不是深度优先遍历和层次遍历
lots of natural things you might try,
并不是那些常用的方式
none of which work in cache oblivious context.
那些方式在缓参无关环境下都无效
This is pretty much the only thing that works.
这可以说是唯一有效的选择
And the intuition as, well,
而直观上来看
we are trying to mimic all kinds of B trees.
我们想要我们的树适用于所有类型的B树
So, if you want a binary tree,
如果你想要一个二叉树
well, that's the original tree.
那好 这本来就是二叉树
It doesn't matter how you store things.
你想用什么方式来存储都行
If you want a tree where the branching factor is four,
如果你想要一个分支是4的树
well, then here it is.
这个就是了
These blocks give you a branching factor of four.
这四个块就是你要的四个分支
If we had more leaves down here,
如果下面有更多的叶节点
there would be four children hanging off of that node.
那么 这下面又会有四个子树
And these are all clustered together consecutively in memory.
而在同一块里的数据 都是连续地存储在内存中
So, if your block size happens to be three,
如果你的内存块大小是3
then this is a perfect way to store things for a block size of three.
那这就是一个内存块为3的完美的解决方案
If you're block size happens to be probably 15,
如果你的块大小是15
right, if we count the number of, right,
那我们来数一数
the number of nodes in here is 15,
这一整块的节点数就是15
if you're block size happens to be 15,
如果你的块大小是15
then this recursion will give you a perfect blocking in terms of 15.
那么这种分配也可以完美地给你大小为15的块
And in general, it's actually mimicking block sizes of 2^2^K-1.
实际上 它适用于块大小为2^2^K-1的情况
Think powers of powers of two. OK, that's the intuition.
2的平方的K次方 好 这是直观的阐述
Let me give you the formal analysis to make it clearer.
下面给出更系统、清楚的分析
So, we claim that there are order, log base B of N memory transfers.
我们已知有O(log_B(N))的存储传输量
That's what we want to prove no matter what B is.
我们想证明的它对于任意B都成立
So here's what we're going to do.
下面就是我们要做的
You may recall last time when we analyzed divide and conquer algorithms,
好好回想一下 上次我们分析分治法的时候
we wrote our recurrence, and that the base case was the key.
在递归循环中 基准情形是关键
Here, in fact, we are only going to
某种意义上 我们关注的
think about the base case in a certain sense.
其实只有基准情形而已
We don't have, really, recursion in the algorithm.
你用不着去跟着递归一步一步走
The algorithm is just walking down some root-to-leaf path.
算法会自己找到一条根到叶子的路径
We only have a recursion in a definition of the layout.
递归过程仅仅出现于存储分布的定义里
So, we can be a little bit more flexible.
所以 我们的想法可以更灵活一些
We don't have to look at our recurrence.
你用不着去盯着递归看
We are just going to think about the base case.
只要考虑基准情形就可以了
I want to imagine, you start with the big triangle.
想象一下 你从这个大三角形开始
That you cut it in the middle; you get smaller triangles.
然后你在中间来了一刀 得到了更小的三角形
Imagine the point at which you keep recursively cutting.
然后你一直这样切下去
So imagine this process.
想象一下这个过程
Big triangles halve in height each time.
大三角形每次都会被拦腰斩断
They're getting smaller and smaller,
然后 三角形越变越小
stop cutting at the point where a triangle fits in a block.
直到三角形的大小正好符合内存块的大小为止
OK, and look at that time.
我们要看的就是这个时候
OK, the recursion actually goes all the way,
当然了 每一步都需要递归分割
but in the analysis let's think about the point
但是在分析里 我们需要考虑则只有
where the chunk fits in a block in one of these triangles,
当三角形和内存块大小吻合的时候
one of these boxes fits in a block.
也就是框起来的节点数与块大小一致的时候
So, I'm going to call this a recursive level.
我们把每一层递归称为递归层级
So, I'm imagining expanding all of the recursions in parallel.
想象一下 我们把一层层的递归平行地展开来
This is some level of detail,
这是一种表示细节的层级
some level of refinement of the trees
或者说表示树被细分的程度
at which the tree you're looking at, the triangle, has size.
我们要考虑的是 当三角形的大小
In other words, there is a
换句话说
number of nodes in that triangle is less than or equal to B.
当三角形中的节点数 小于等于B的时候
OK, so let me draw a picture.
我来画上一笔
So, I want to draw sort of this picture but where instead of nodes,
我想要画的和这幅图的差不多 不过我不用节点
I have little triangles of size, at most, B.
而是用三角形 它们大小最大是B
So, the picture looks something like this.
我们的图大概会是这样
We have a little triangle of size, at most, B.
我们有一个小三角形 最大是B
It has a bunch of children which are
它下面有一些子树
subtrees of sizeat most, B, the same size.
它们的大小也同样是B
And then, these are in a chunk, and then we have other chunks
这些是一组 然后还有其他的组
that look like that in recursion potentially.
和上面的基本一样
OK, so I haven't drawn everything.
我就不一一画全了
There would be a whole bunch of, between B and B^2,
其实中间还有很多子树  数量在B到B^2之间
in fact, subtrees, other squares of this size.
呃 是子树大小的平方才对
So here, I had to refine the entire tree here.
我要先对整个树在中间进行了细分
And then I refined each of the subtrees here and here at these levels.
然后再对这些子树的这里 和这里 进行细分
And then it turned out after these two recursive levels,
经过了这两级递归 我们发现
everything fits in a block.
这些三角形就和内存块大小一样了
Everything has the same size,
每个三角形大小都一样
so at some point they will all fit within a block.
到某个时候它们就和内存块大小一样了
And they might actually be quite a bit smaller than the block.
不过也有可能它们会比内存块要小一些
How small?
到底有多小？
So, what I'm doing is cutting
我所做的其实就是
the number of levels in half at each point.
每次把树对半分割
And I stop when the height of one of these trees is
一直到这些树的高度
essentially at most log B because that's when the number
小于等于log B时候 我才停止分割
of nodes at there will be B roughly.
因为这时子树的节点数大约为B
So, how small can the height be?
那么高度最小是多少？
I keep dividing at half and stopping when it's, at most, log B.
我一直不停地分割下去 一直到树高≤ B为止
Log B over two.
最小是log B/2
So it's, at most, log B, it's at least half log B.
所以高度最大是log B 最小是log B/2
Therefore, the number of nodes
所以子树的节点数
it here could be between the square root of B and B.
可能是√B到B之间
So, this could be a lot smaller and less than a constant factor
所以 子树的节点数可能会远小于
of a block, a claim that doesn't matter.
一个块的的大小 不过这无关紧要
It's OK. This could be a small square root of B.
都是可以的 它的大小可能是√B
I'm not even going to write that it could be a small square root of B
我甚至都不想把它可能是√B写出来
because that doesn't play a role in the analysis.
因为在分析里它是打酱油的
It's a worry, but it's OK
这是个隐患 不过可以接受
essentially because our bound only involves log B.
本质上因为我们的定界只跟以B为底的log有关
It doesn't involve B.
而不是和B有关
So, here's what we do.
回过来总结一下
We know that each of the height of one of these triangles
我们知道对于这些节点数≤B的三角形
of size, at most, B is at least a half log B.
它们的高度大于等于log B/2
And therefore, if you look at a search path,
因此 如果你观察一条搜索路径
so, when we do a search in this tree,
当我们在树里进行搜索时
we're going to start up here.
我们应该从这里开始
And I'm going to mess up the diagram now.
我又开始毁图了
We're going to follow some path,
我们沿着某一条路径
maybe I should have drawn it going down here.
或许应该是往这边走
We visit through some of these triangles,
我们访问了这些三角形
but it's a root-to-node path in the tree.
不过实际上这是一条根到节点的路径
So, how many of the triangles could it visit?
那么我们一共访问了多少三角形？
Well, the height of the tree divided by
答案是 树的高度——
the height of one of the triangles.
除以三角形的高度
So, this visits, at most, log N over half log B triangles,
访问的三角形个数最多是log N / (½ log B)
which looks good. This is log base B of N,
哎哟 不错喔 这就是以B为底的log N
mind you off factor of two.
当然前面还有个2
Now, what we worry about is how many blocks does a triangle occupy?
现在 我们想知道一个三角形要占用几个块？
One of these triangles should fit in a block. But..
某些三角形应该正好只占用一个内存块  但是呢
We know by the recursive layout,
我们知道在递归分布中
it is stored in a consecutive region in memory.
这是三角形是储存在一段连续的内存区域里的
So, how many blocks could occupy?
那么 三角形最多可能占用几个块？
Two, because of alignment,
两个 因为在数据对齐时
it might fall across the boundary of a block,
某个三角形可能正好落在块的边界上
but at most, one boundary.
不过最多也只有一个边界
So, it fits in two blocks.
所以 两个块能妥妥地装下
So, each triangle fits in one block,
每个三角形都能装在一个块里
but is in, at most, two blocks,
不过有时候会占用到两个块
memory blocks, size B depending on alignment.
两个内存块 大小是B 取决于数据对齐的情况
So, the number of memory transfers, in other words,
所以传输的内存量 换而言之
a number of blocks we read,
也就是读取的块的个数——
because all we are doing here is reading in a search,
因为搜索实际就是在读取
is at most two blocks per triangle.
——每个三角形最多占用两个块
There are this many triangles,
算上这么多三角形的
so it's at most, 4 log base B of N,
最多是4 log_B(N)
OK, which is order log base B of N.
也就是O(log_B(n))
And there are papers about decreasing this constant 4
有些论文专门研究如何把降低这个常数4
with more sophisticated data structures.
用的是更复杂的数据结构
You can get it down to a little bit less than two I think.
我觉得起码能降低得比2要小
So, there you go. So not quite as good as B trees
但就这样了 这个其实并没有B树那么好
in terms of the constant, but pretty good.
因为有这个常数 不过已经不错了
And what's good is that this data structure
而这个数据结构的精妙之处在于
works for all B at the same time.
对于所有B值都有效
This analysis works for all B.
这个分析对于所有的B都成立
So, we have a multilevel memory hierarchy, no problem.
所以 我们可以轻松应对多层内存结构
Any questions about this data structure?
对于这个数据结构还有什么问题？
This is already pretty sophisticated,
这货的难度已经是困难了
but we are going to get even more sophisticated.
不过接下来的会是噩梦级别的
Next, OK, good, no questions.
很好 大家都很淡定
This is either perfectly clear, or a little bit difficult,or both.
你们是都无压力 还是已经GG？  我看是不明觉厉
So, now, I debated with myself sometime
有时我自己会思想斗争
what exactly I would cover next.
来决定我们下面要讲什么
There are two natural things I could cover,
有两个东西都很有必要讲
both of which are complicated.
但两个都挺复杂的
My first result in the cache oblivious world is
我在缓参无关算法中地第一个成果
making this data structure dynamic.
就是让这个数据结构动态化
So, there is a dynamic B tree that's cache oblivious
所以 有一种动态的B树 是缓参无关的
that works for all values of B.
而且它对所有的B值适用
And it gets log base B of N, insert, delete, and search.
而且插入删除和搜索的花费都是log_B(N)
So, this just gets search in log base B of N.
我们前面说的只是用log_B(N)的搜索
That data structure, our first paper was damn complicated,
我们第一篇论文的数据结构超级复杂
and then it got simplified.
后来简化了一些
It's now not too hard, but it takes
现在就没那么难了
a couple of lectures in an advanced algorithms class to teach it.
不过依然需要很多节高级算法课才能讲清楚
So, I'm not going to do that.
所以这里我就不为难你们了
But there you go. It exists.
但这算法是确实存在的
Instead, we're going to cover our favorite problem sorting
而我们要讲的是大家喜闻乐见的排序
in the cache oblivious context.
在缓存无关的环境下的排序
And this is quite complicated, more than you'd expect,
这其实相当复杂 比你们想象的难
OK, much more complicated than it is
甚至比在多线程环境下
in a multithreaded setting to get the right answer, anyway.
更难做出正确的分析
Maybe to get the best answer in
虽说在多线程环境下
a multithreaded setting is also complicated.
要得出最佳的分析也挺难的
The version we got last week was pretty easy.
不过我们上周做的那个就很简单
But before we go to cache oblivious sorting,
在我们讲缓存无关排序之前
let me talk about cache aware sorting
我们先来讲讲缓存相关排序
because we need to know what bound we are aiming for.
因为我们需要知道 我们的优化边界是什么
And just to warn you,
我先声明一点
I may not get to the full analysis of
我不会对整个缓存无关排序
the full cache oblivious sorting.
做完整的分析
But I want to give you an idea
但我想给你们讲解
of what goes into it because it's pretty cool, I think,
它内在的思想 因为它实在太酷炫了
a lot of ideas.
蕴含了很多想法
So, how might you sort?
那么 你们是怎么排序的？
So, cache aware, we assume we can do everything.
在缓存相关环境下 假设我们能做任何事
Basically, this means we have B trees.
也就是说 我们有B树
That's the only other structure we know.
这是我们手上唯一的数据结构
How would you sort N numbers,
如果你只有B树
given that that's the only data structure you have?
你要怎么对N个数排序？
Right, just add them into the B tree,
没错 就是把他们都插入到B树中
and then do an in-order traversal.
然后按中序遍历
That's one way to sort, perfectly reasonable.
这是一种不错的排序方式 非常合理
We'll call it repeated insertion into a B tree.
我们称之为 B树反复插入
OK, we know in the usual setting, and the BST sort,
我们知道 在通常情况下 比如BST排序
where you use a balanced binary search tree,
它用的是平衡二叉搜索树
like red-black trees, that takes N log N time, log N per operation,
像红黑树什么的 总排序时间为N log N 每步花费log N
and that's an optimal sorting algorithm in the comparison model,
这在比较型排序算法里是最优情况了
only thinking about comparison model here.
这里我们只考虑比较型排序算法
So, how many memory transfers does this data structure takes?
那么 这种数据结构有多少内存传输？
Sorry, this algorithm for sorting?
说错了 是这种排序算法有多少内存传输？
The number of memory transfers is a function of N and B
内存传输MT是一个关于N和B的函数
and MT is?
那MT是多少？
This is easy.
其实挺简单的
N insertions, OK, you have to think about N order traversal.
有N次插入 你得联想一下N阶的遍历
You have to remember back your analysis of B trees,
再回想一下对B树的分析
but this is not too hard.
但这并不难
How long does the insertion take, the N insertions?
N次插入要多久？
N log base B of N.
N log_B(N)
How long does the traversal take? Less time.
那遍历要多久？ 比这更少
If we think about it, you can get away with N over B memory transfers,
仔细想想的话 我们其实只需要N/B次内存传输
so quite a bit less than this.
所以要比这个小
This is bigger than N, which is actually pretty bad.
而这个比N要大 所以它弱爆了
N memory transfers means essentially you're doing random access,
内存传输量为N的算法 就相当于在做随机访问
visiting every element in some random order.
按随机的顺序访问每个元素
It's even worse. There's even a log factor.
这个比它还差 后面还挂着个log因子
Now, the log factor goes down by this log B factor.
虽然log_B(N)会随着B的增加而减小
But, this is actually a really bad sorting bound.
但这也是一个相当糟糕的边界
So, unlike normal algorithms,
和普通算法不一样的是
where using a search tree is a good way to sort,
一般来说 用搜索树来排序是个好方法
in cache oblivious or cache aware sorting it's really, really bad.
但是在考虑到缓存的时候 它就很糟糕了
So, what's another natural algorithm you might try,
还有什么值得一试的算法吗？
given what we know for sorting?
在我们已知的排序算法里？
And, even cache oblivious,
即使是缓存无关的也行
all the algorithms we've seen are cache oblivious.
其实我们学过的算法都是缓存无关的
So, what's a good one to try? Merge sort.
哪个值得一试？ 归并排序
OK, we did merge sort in multithreaded algorithms.
我们在多线程里讲过归并排序
Let's try a merge sort, a good divide and conquer thing.
那我们就来试试归并排序 分治法的典范
So, I'm going to call it binary merge sort
我把它称为二分归并排序
because it splits the array into two pieces,
因为这里我们把数组分成两半
and it recurses on the two pieces.
然后再递归地分割这两半数组
So, you get a binary recursion tree.
于是 你就得到了一个二分递归树
So, let's analyze it.
我们来分析一下
So the number of memory transfers on N elements,
那么 N个元素所需的内存传输量
so I mean it has a pretty good recursive layout, right?
这个结构的递归分布已经很不错了 是吧？
The two subarrays that we get
因为我们分割数组的时候
when we partition our array are consecutive.
得到的两个子数组在内存里是连续的
So, we're recursing on this, recursing on this.
然后再对这边递归 对这边递归
So, it's a nice cache oblivious layout.
所以 这是个很好的缓参无关分布
And this is even for cache aware.
即使在缓存相关时
This is a pretty good algorithm,
这依然是很好的算法
a lot better than this one, as we'll see.
比这个要强多了 后面会说到
But, what is the recurrence we get?
那它的递归式是什么？
So, here we have to go back to last lecture when we were
这里我们就得回头看看上一课
thinking about recurrences for recursive cache oblivious algorithms.
好好回想下缓参无关算法的递归式
I mean, the first part should be pretty easy.
第一步应该无压力吧
There's an O. Well, OK, let's put the O at the end,
有个"O"？ 啊 好吧 我们最后再说"O"
the divide and the conquer part at the end.
最后再考虑分治的部分
The recursion is 2MT of N over two, good.
而这里的递归式则是 2MT(N/2) 很好
All right, that's just like the merge sort recurrence,
就像归并排序的递归式一样
and that's the additive term that you're thinking about.
然后就是你们说的附加项了
OK, so normally, we would pay a linear additive term here,
一般来说 我们要加一个线性的附加项
order N because merging takes order N time.
阶是N 因为归并的时间是N阶的
Now, we are merging, which is three parallel scans,
现在我们来做归并 这会有三个并行的扫描
the two inputs and the output.
两个输入用 一个输出用
OK, they're not quite parallel interleaved.
它们不是一般的并行交错地扫描
They're a bit funnily interleaved,
而是以一个奇怪的方式交错扫描
but as long as your cache stores at least three blocks,
但只要你的缓存能放得下三个块
this is also linear time in this setting,
在这里的花费就会是线性的时间
which means you visit each block a constant number of times.
也就是说 对于每个块 访问次数都是固定的
OK, that's the recurrence.
这就是递归式了
Now, we also need a base case, of course.
当然我们还需要一个基准情形
We've seen two base cases, one MT of B, and the other,
我们见过两个基准情形 一个是MT(B)
MT of whatever fits in cache.
另一个就是能匹配缓存大小的MT
So, let's look at that one because it's better.
这里我们考虑后一个 因为它更好
So, for some constant, C, if I have an array of size M,
假设我有一个大小为M的数组 对于某常数c
this fits in cache, actually, probably C is one here,
cM与缓存大小相匹配 这个c也可能是1
but I'll just be careful.
不过我还是严谨一点
For some constant, this fits in cache.
对于某常数c来说 cM和缓存大小匹配
A problem of this size fits in cache, and in that case,
当问题分割到跟缓存大小匹配时
the number of memory transfers is, anyone remember?
它的内存传输量是多少？ 有谁记得？
We've used this base case more than once before.
我们已经不止一次讨论过这个基准情形了
Do you remember?
听说你记得？
Sorry? CM over B.
什么？ cM/B
I've got a big O, so M over B.
因为这是大O记号 所以是O(M/B)
Order M over B because this is the size of the data.
O(M/B)可以理解为 M是数据的大小
So, I mean, just to read it all in takes M over B.
而把所有数据读入缓存要M/B次
Once it's in cache,
一旦数据读入缓存以后
it doesn't really matter what I do as long as
只要把每cM的数据 存储在线性的空间中
I use linear space for the right constant here.
那我做什么都不会有额外的花费
As long as I use linear space in that algorithm,
只要算法是线性地使用缓存空间
I'll stay in cache, and therefore,
那就可以把数据留在缓存里 也因此
not have to write anything out until the very end
直到数据处理完毕 我都不需要写回
and I spend M over B to write it out.
最终我花费M/B来写回
OK, so I can't really spend more than M over B
所以无论我用的是什么算法
almost no matter what algorithm I have,
我用的内存传输都不会大于M/B
so long as it uses linear space.
只要算法是线性地使用缓存空间
So, this is a base case that's useful pretty much in any algorithm.
这个基准情形对大多数算法都是有用的
OK, that's a recurrence.
那么 这就是递归式了
Now we just have to solve it.
现在我们来解它
OK, let's see how good binary merge sort is.
好的 我们就来看看二分归并到底有多威武
OK, and again, I'm going to just give the intuition
我重申 这里我只会直观地讲一下
behind the solution to this recurrence.
这个递归式解法的内在思想
And I won't use the substitution method to prove it formally.
我不会给出用代入法的正式证明
But this one's actually pretty simple.
不过这个其实挺简单的
So, we have, at the top, actually I'm going to write it over here.
在第一层递归里——我还是写在这边吧
Otherwise I won't be able to see.
不然我都快看不着了
So, at the top of the recursion,
所以在第一层递归时
we have N over B costs.
我们的花费是N/B
I'll ignore the constants.
常数什么的就不管了
There is probably also on additive one, which I'm ignoring here.
后面可能还有一个1 不过先无视它
Then we split into two problems of half the size.
然后我们把它分成两个子问题
So, we get a half N over B, and a half N over B.
所以 每个子问题大小都是 ½ N/B
OK, usually this was N, half N, half N.
在以前 这里是N 然后这两个是N/2
You should remember it as from lecture one.
第一节课的式子就是这样的
So, the total on this level is N over B.
所以这一层的和是N/B
The total on this level is N over B.
这层的和也一样是N/B
And, you can prove by induction,
你可以用归纳法证明
that every level is N over B.
每一层都是N/B
The question is how many levels are there?
问题是一共有多少层？
Well, at the bottom, so, dot, dot, dot,
那在最底层 点 点 点
at the bottom of this recursion tree
我们直接看递归树的最底层
we should get something of size M
数据的大小应该是M
and then we're paying M over B.
然后它的传输花费是M/B
Actually here we're paying M over B.
就像这里写的 花费是M/B
So, it's a good thing those match. They should.
他们应该是相互匹配的
So here, we have a bunch of leaves, all the size M over B.
所以 这些叶子节点的大小都是M/B
You can also compute the number of leaves here is N over M.
你也可以算出来 这些叶节点的个数是N/M
If you want to be extra sure, you should always check the leaf level.
为了确保没算错 你就要检查叶子层的花费和
It's a good idea.
这是个好习惯
So we have N over M leaves, each costing M over B.
我们有N/M个节点 每个花费都是M/B
This is an M. So, this is N over B also.
这个M消掉 所以 这层的花费还是N/B
So, every level here is N over B memory transfers.
所以每一层的内存传输量都是N/B
And the number of levels is one? N over B?
那么层数是多少呢？ 1？ N/B？
Log N over B. Yep, that's right.
log(N/B) 这才是正确答案
I just didn't hear it right.
刚刚应该是我听错了
OK, we are starting at N.
一开始 数据大小为N
We're getting down to M.
到最后分割成大小为M
So, you can think of it as log N, the whole binary tree
你可以理解为 整个二叉树的高度是log N
minus the subtrees log M,
减去最下面子树的高度log M
and that's the same as log N over M,
结果就是log(N/M)
OK, or however you want to think about it.
你还可以有别的理解方式
The point is that this is a log base two.
关键是这个log是以2为底的
That's where we are not doing so great.
就是这个地方还不够给力
So this is actually a pretty good algorithm.
不过这个算法已经很不错了
So let me write the solution over here.
我们来写一遍过程
So, the number of memory transfers on N items is going to be
所以 N个元素的内存传输量应该是...
the number of levels times the cost of each level.
层数乘以每层的花费
So, this is N over B times log base two of N over M,
所以就是N/B乘以log_2(N/M)
which is a lot better than repeated insertion into a B tree.
这就比对B树的反复插入要好得多
Here, we were getting N times log N over log B,
这里我们得到的是N*log N/log B
OK, so N log N over log B.
对于这个N*log N/log B
We're getting a log B savings over not proving anything,
即使它有个分母log B 但也说明不了什么
and here we are getting a factor of B savings, N log N over B.
而这条式的分母是B 所以是N*log N/B
In fact, we even made it a little bit smaller by dividing this N by M.
而且后面的log(N/M)比log N还要小一点呢
That doesn't matter too much.
当然这不是重点
This dividing by B is a big one.
重点是分母还是个大(牛)B
OK, so we're almost there.
好了 我们很接近最优解了
This is almost an optimal algorithm.
这已经差不多是个最优算法了
It's even cache oblivious, which is pretty cool.
而且它还是缓参无关的 好感度+10
And that extra little step, which is that
再努力一点点
you should be able to get another log B factor improvement,
你就能得到一个log B因子的性能提升
I want to combine these two ideas.
我要结合这两个算法
I want to keep this factor B improvement over N log N,
我既想保留这个优化分母B
and I want to keep this factor log B improvement over N log N,
我同时还想保留这个优化分母log B
and get them together.
兼得鱼与熊掌
So, first, before we do that cache obliviously,
在我们把它做成缓参无关之前
let's do it cache aware.
我们先来看看缓存相关的情况
So, this is the third cache aware algorithm.
这已经是第三个缓存相关算法了
This one was also cache oblivious.
而这个算法(归并排序)同时也是缓参无关的
So, how should I modify a merge sort in order to do better?
那么 我们如何改进归并排序呢？
I mean, I have this log base two,
我的意思是 这个log是以2为底的
and I want a log base B, more or less.
我大致是想要以B为底的
So, how would I do that with merge sort?
那么 我们怎么改进归并排序？
Yeah? Split into B subarrays,
请说？分成B份
yeah. Instead of doing binary merge sort,
没错 原来我们做的是二分归并
this is what I was hinting at here,
我之前也说明过
instead of splitting it into two pieces,
我们之前是把数据分成两份
and recursing on the two pieces, and then merging them,
之后递归地分下去 然后再把它们归并
I could split potentially into more pieces.
其实 我们可以试试分成更多份
OK, and to do that, I'm going to use my cache.
好吧 于是我们要用到缓存了
So the idea is B pieces.
分成B份是一个思路
This is actually not the best thing to do,
但不是最优的选择
although B pieces does work.
尽管分成B份也行
And, it's what I was hinting at because I was saying I want a log B.
因为我一直在埋伏笔说要一个log B
It's actually not quite log B. It's log M over B.
但其实这不是log B啦 而是log(M/B)
OK, but let's see. So, what is the most pieces I could split into?
我们一步步看 那么 我们最多能分成几份？
Right, well, i could split into N pieces.
好吧 我大可以分成N份
That would be good, wouldn't it, at only one recursive level?
这不是省力更省心？ 一次递归就完事了
I can't split into N pieces. Why?
事实上我不能这么干 原因呢？
What happens wrong when I split into N pieces?
要是分成了N份会有什么后果？
That would be the ultimate.
感觉这才是它的完全体啊？
You can't merge, exactly.
因为你归并不了 就是这样
So, if I have N pieces, you can't merge in cache.
如果有N份 那归并就无法在缓存中进行
I mean, so in order to merge in cache,
因为如果归并要在缓存内进行
what I need is to be able to store an entire block
我就必须从每一个归并队列里
from each of the lists that I'm merging.
都取出一个完整的数据块存入缓存里
If I can store an entire block in cache for each of the lists,
如果每一个队列都有一个完整的块在缓存里
then it's a bunch of parallel scans.
那么就能进行并行扫描了
So this is like testing the limit of parallel scanning technology.
这就像是在测试并行扫描技术的极限
If you have K parallel scans,
如果你有K个并行的扫描
and you can fit K blocks in cache,
并且缓存里有K个对应的块
then all is well because you can scan through
那就万事大吉了 因为这样你就可以
each of those K arrays, and have one block from
并行地扫描K个数组 而对于每个数组
each of the K arrays in cache at the same time.
每次都有一个数据块在缓存里
So, that's the idea.
所以 这就是原因了
Now, how many blocks can I fit in cache?
那么 我能在缓存里装多少块？
M over B. That's the biggest I could do.
M/B 不能再多了
So this will give the best running time among
所以这也决定了归并排序
these kinds of merge sort algorithms.
它的最佳运行时间
This is an M over B way merge sort.
这就是M/B路的归并排序
OK, so now we get somewhat better recurrence.
现在 我们得到的是一个更好的递归
We split into M over B subproblems now, each of size,
我们把它拆分成M/B个子问题
well, it's N divided by M over B without thinking.
毫无疑问 每个大小都是N/(M/B)
And, the claim is that the merge time is still linear
而且归并的时间依然是线性的
because we have barely enough,
因为缓存刚好够用
OK, maybe I should describe this algorithm.
我觉得应该把这个算法描述一遍
So, we divide, because we've never really done non-binary merge sort.
我们先分解 因为我们没真正做过多路归并排序
We divide into M over B equal size subarrays instead of two.
把数据拆分为M/B个等大的子队列 而不是两个
Here, we are clearly doing a cache aware algorithm.
显然这是一个缓存相关的算法
We are assuming we know what M over B is.
假设M/B是已知的
So, then we recursively sort each subarray,
然后 我们递归地对每个子序列排序
and then we conquer. We merge.
然后再做归并
And, the reason(why)merge works is
我们之所以能够归并
because we can afford one block in cache.
是因为我们能保证 在缓存里面
So, let's call it one cache block per subarray.
一个子序列至少有一个缓存块
OK, actually, if you're careful, you also need one block
而且如果你细心的话 你会发现
for the output of the merged array before you write it out.
你还需要一个缓存块来存放输出结果
So, it should be M over B minus one.
所以应该是M/B-1
But, let's ignore some additive constants.
不过现在先不考虑这个常数项
OK, so this is the recurrence we get.
那么 这就是我们得到的递归式
The base case is the same. And, what improves here?
基准情形是一样的 那改进在什么地方呢？
I mean, the per level cost doesn't change,
因为每层的花费没变
I claim, because at the top we get N over B.
在顶层 我们的数据大小是N/B
This does before. Then we split into M over B subproblems,
这和以前一样 然后我们把它分成了M/B个子问题
each of which costs a one over M over B factor times N over B.
每个子问题的花费都是1/(M/B)*N/B
OK, so you add all those up,
把它们加在一起
you still get N over B because we are not decreasing the number
你得到的还是N/B 因为我们并没有减少数据
of elements. We're just splitting them.
我们只是把它分割开
There's now M over B subproblems,
现在有M/B个子问题
each of one over M over B the size.
每个的大小都是M/B
So, just like before, each level will sum to N over B.
就像前面讲过的 每层的花费总和都是N/B
What changes is the number of levels
发生变化的是层的个数
because now we have bigger branching factor.
因为分支的数量增加了
Instead of log base two,
这次的log不是以2为底
it's now log base the branching factor.
而是以分支数为底
So, the height of this tree is log base M over B of N over M,
那么这个树的高度就是log_(M/B)(N/M)
I believe. Let me make sure that agrees with me.
应该是这样 我使用道具[小抄]确认一下
Yeah.
就是这样喵~
OK, and if you're careful,
细心的你可能会发现
this counts not quite the number of levels,
这其实不是准确的层数
but the number of levels minus one.
而是层数减1(因为还有最顶层)
So, I'm going to one plus one here.
所以我再加上1
And the reason why is this is not quite the bound that I want.
但这个并不是我理想的边界 原因是...
Let me rewrite it a liittle bit.
我改写一下这条式子
So, we have log base M over B.
首先 我们有log以M/B为底——
What I really want, actually, is N over B.
我这么做的真正的目标 是得到N/B
I claim that these are the same because we have minus,
这里的等号是成立的 因为我后面还要减一项
yeah, that's good.
嗯 很好
OK, this should come as rather mysterious,
这有点神来之笔的感觉
but it's because I know what the sorting bound
但其实是因为我非常熟悉排序的边界
should be as I'm doing this arithmetic.
所以 算一算就看出来了
So, I'm taking log base M over B of N over M.
我把这个log_(M/B)(N/M)
I'm not changing the base of the log.
保持它底不变
I'm just saying, well, N over M,
看这里 N/M
that is N over B divided by M over B because then the B's cancel,
它可以化成N/B除以M/B  因为B可以消掉
and the M goes on the bottom.
M就被分离出来
So, if I do that in the logs,
再对它们取对数
I get log of N over B minus log of M over B
就变成了log(N/B)-log(M/B)
minus because I'm dividing.
这里的除法变减法
OK, now, log base M over B of M over B is one.
而log_(M/B)(M/B)又等于1
So, these cancel, and I get log base M over B, N over B,
所以后面两个消掉了 我就得到了log_(M/B)(N/B)
which is what I was aiming for.
这正是我想要的
Why? Because that's the right bound as it's normally written.
为什么？ 因为这就是正常情况下的边界值
OK, that's what we will be trying to get cache obliviously.
我们想在缓参无关的条件下取得这个界
So, that's the height of the search tree,
那么 我们知道了树的高度
and at each level we are paying N over B memory transfers.
又知道每层的内存传输都是N/B
So, the overall number of memory transfers
所以 总的内存传输量就是
for this M over B way merge sort is the sorting bound.
这个M/B分归并算法的复杂度的边界
This is, I'll put it in a box. This is the sorting bound,
我把它框起来 这就是算法的复杂度的边界
and it's very special because it is the optimal number of
它的特殊之处在于 在缓存相关的条件下
memory transfers for sorting N items cache aware.
这是N元排序算法复杂度最优的边界了
This has been known since, like, 1983.
这是在1983年提出来的
OK, this is the best thing to do.
这是我们能做到的最好结果了
It's a really weird bound,
这个边界看起来很奇怪
but if you ignore all the divided by B's,
不过如果你无视掉这些分母B
it's sort of like N times log base M of N.
它就变成了N*log_M(N)
So, that's little bit more reasonable.
这看起来就科学多了
But, there's lots of divided by B's.
不过实际的式子里有很多B
So, the number of the blocks in the input
输入的块的数量 乘以
times log base the number of blocks
以缓存的块数为底的
in the cache of the number of blocks in the input.
输入的块数量的对数
That's a little bit more intuitive.
这样解释更直观一些
That is the bound. And that's what we are aiming for.
这个就是我们想要的边界
So, this algorithm, crucially,
这算法的关键在于
assume that we knew what M over B was.
这是在我们已知M/B的前提下
Now, we are going to try and do it without knowing M over B,
现在我们要试着做做不知道M/B的情况
do it cache obliviously.
也就是缓存无关
And that is the result of only a few years ago.
这个结果是前几年才做出来的
Are you ready?
准备好了吗？
Everything clear so far? It's a pretty natural algorithm.
没问题吧？ 这还是很好理解的
We were going to try to mimic it essentially and do a merge sort,
我们想要模仿它的原理 然后做一个新的归并排序
but not M over B way merge sort because we don't know how.
不过这次不是M/B路了 因为M/B是未知的
We're going to try and do it essentially
我们要做的是
a square root of N way merge sort.
√N路的归并排序
If you play around, that's the natural thing to do.
你瞎蒙也能蒙出这个数
The tricky part is that it's hard to merge square root of N
不过问题在于 你很难同时归并√N路数据
lists at the same time, in a cache efficient way.
因为这样就不好高效地利用缓存了
We know that if the square root of N is bigger than M over B,
我们刚才讲过 如果√N大于M/B的话
you're hosed if you just do a straightforward merge.
你要直接同时归并√N路就是在找抽
So, we need a fancy merge.
所以 我们需要巧妙地归并
We are going to do a divide and conquer merge.
我们要分而治之地归并
It's a lot like the multithreaded algorithms of last week,
就像上周做的多线程算法一样
try and do a divide and conquer merge so that
我们尝试一种分治型归并
no matter how many lists are merging,
不管归并队列有多少个
as long as it's less than the square root of N,
只要少于√N个 准确来说是³√N个
or actually cubed root of N, we can do it cache efficiently,
我们都可以高效地利用缓存完成归并
OK? So, we'll do this, we need a bit of setup.
好的 我们首先需要一些前提条件
But that's where we're going, cache oblivious sorting.
而我们的方向就是缓参无关的排序
So, we want to get the sorting bound, and, yeah.
然后 我们想得到这一个排序复杂度的边界
It turns out, to do cache oblivious sorting,
你会发现 在做缓参无关排序时
you need an assumption about the cache size.
你需要估计一下缓存的大小
This is kind of annoying, because we said, well,
这点相当哲学 因为我们一边说
cache oblivious algorithms should work
既然是缓存无关算法
for all values of B and all values of M.
那就应该对所有缓存参数B和M都好使
But, you can actually prove you need an additional assumption
但其实你还必须有一个额外的参数估计
in order to get this bound cache obliviously.
才能在缓参无关的条件下得到这个边界
That's the result of, like, last year by Garrett Brodel.
这个结果应该是去年由Garrett Brodel提出来的
So, and the assumption is, well, the assumption is fairly weak.
这个估计就是——这个估计其实很弱
That's the good news.
这是个好消息
OK, we've actually made an assumption several times.
我们以前也做过几次估计
We said, well, assuming the cache can store at least three blocks,
比如说 假设缓存至少可以存下三个块
or assuming the cache can store at least four blocks,
或者四个块
yeah, it's reasonable to say the cache can store at least four blocks,
如果说缓存至少能放进四个块或者某常数个块
or at least any constant number of blocks.
这也算是说得过去的
This is that the number of blocks that your cache can store
这条式子就是说 缓存里能容纳的块数
is at least B to the epsilon blocks.
至少是B的ε次方
This is saying your cache isn't, like, really narrow.
意思就是你的缓存不是细而短
It's about as tall as it is wide.
而是粗又壮的
This actually gives you a lot of sloth.
这样我们就可以舒服多了
And, we're going to use a simple version of this assumption
我们可以用这个公式的简化版
that M is at least B^2.
假设M大于等于B^2
OK, this is pretty natural. It's saying that your cache is
这个很好理解 就是说你的缓存
at least as tall as it is wide where these are the blocks.
高度至少跟宽度一样大 这些一条条的就是块
OK, the number of blocks is it least the size of a block.
也就是说块的数量大于等于块的大小
That's a pretty reasonable assumption,
这个假设很合理
and if you look at caches these days, they all satisfy this,
现今我们用的缓存都符合这一点
at least for some epsilon. Pretty much universally,
至少对某个ε成立 而且绝大数情况下
M is at least B^2 or so. OK, and in fact,
M至少应该是B^2  事实上
if you think from our speed of light arguments from last time,
如果你还记得上次我说过的光速限制理论
B^2 or B^3 is actually the right thing to do.
B^2或者说B^3是有道理的
As you go out, I guess in 3-D,
因为在三维空间中
B^2 would be the surface area of the sphere out there.
B^2就是球形的表面
OK, so this is actually the natural thing of how much space
这就可以理解为 给定一个距离
you should have at a particular distance.
对应的球形的面积(体积)是多少
Assuming we live in a constant dimensional space,
假设我们住在一个常数维的空间中
that assumption would be true.
这个假设就是成立的
This even allows going up to 42 dimensions or whatever,
这个结论甚至适用于42维的空间
OK, so a pretty reasonable assumption. Good.
所以这个假设还很合理 很好
Now, we are going to achieve this bound.
现在 我们要去取得这个边界
And what we are going to try to do is use
我们要做的就是
an N to the epsilon way merge sort for some epsilon.
使用一个N^ε路的归并排序
And, if we assume that M is at least B^2,
如果M大于等于B^2
the epsilon will be one third, it turns out.
那ε就是三分之一
So, we are going to do the cubed root of N way merge sort.
我们要做的就是³√N分的归并排序
I'll start by giving you and analyzing the sorting algorithms,
我们从排序算法的分析入手
assuming that we know how to do merge in a particular bound.
先假设我们知道 如何在特定的复杂度边界内做归并
OK, then we'll do the merge.
然后 我再来说怎么做归并
The merge is the hard part. OK, so the merge,
而归并才是关键部分
I'm going to give you the black box first of all.
我先给出一个归并的黑盒
what does merge do?
归并是干什么的？
The K way merger is called the K funnel just
K路归并又叫做K漏斗
because it looks like a funnel, which you'll see.
因为它的作用就像一个漏斗 等会儿就知道了
So, a K funnel is a data structure, or is an algorithm,
K漏斗是一种数据结构 或者说是算法
let's say, that looks like a data structure.
因为它看起来像是数据结构
And it merges K sorted lists.
它把K个有序的序列归并到一起
So, supposing you already have K lists, and they're sorted,
假设你有K个有序序列
and assuming that the lists are relatively long,
而且它们都是很长的序列
so we need some additional assumptions for this black box to work,
那使用这个黑盒就需要一些附加条件
and we'll be able to get them as we sort.
这些条件在排序时就会获得
We want the total size of those lists.
我们需要这些序列的总大小
You add up all the elements in all the lists,
假设把所有序列里的所有元素加起来
it should have size at least K^3 is the assumption.
总大小应该至少有K^3这么多
Then, it merges these lists using essentially the sorting bound.
那么 这些序列的归并花费就是这个排序的界
Actually, I should really say theta K^3.
这里应该是Θ(K^3)
I also don't want to be too much bigger than K^3.
我也不希望它比K^3大太多
Sorry about that.
失误了
So, the number of memory transfers that this funnel merger uses is
所以 这个归并漏斗的内存传输量就是
the sorting bound on K^3, so K^3 over B,
K^3个元素对应的排序边界
log base M over B of K^3 over B, plus another K memory transfers.
就是(K^3/B)*log_(M/B)(K^3/B) + K
Now, K memory transfers is pretty reasonable.
后面的这个K很好理解
You've got to at least start reading each list,
一开始 每个序列你都要读取一个块
so you got to pay one memory transfer per list.
所以每个序列都要花一次内存传输
but our challenge in some sense will be getting rid of this plus K
那么 去掉这个K就是一个分支任务了
This is how fast we can merge.
而这就是我们做归并的速度了
We'll do that after.
我们后面再讲
Now, assuming we have this,
现在 先假设这个是已知的
let me tell you how to sort.
我们来讲讲怎么排序
This is, eventually enough, called funnel sort.
它有一个很贴切的名字 漏斗排序
But in a certain sense, it's really cubed root of N way merge sort.
不过实际上它就是³√N路的归并排序
OK, but we'll analyze it using this.
但分析时 我们会用这个名字
OK, so funnel sort, we are going to define K to be
漏斗排序 就是定义K=N^(1/3)
N to the one third, and apply this merger.
然后代入到这个归并中
So, what do we do? It's just like here.
那我们要做什么？ 就像这里
We're going to divide our array into N to the one third.
我们把序列分成N^(1/3)份
I mean, it they should be consecutive subarrays.
这些子序列应该都是连续的
I'll call them segments of the array.
我把它们称作序列片段
OK, for cache oblivious,
对于缓参无关来说
it's really crucial how these things are laid out.
这些东西的内存分布形式至关重要
We're going to cut and get consecutive chunks of the array,
我们把连续的数组着切成几段
N to the one third of them.
一共有N^(1/3)段
Then I'm going to recursively sort them,
然后对它们进行递归排序
and then I'm going to merge.
然后再归并
OK, and I'm going to merge using the K funnel,
我用K漏斗来做归并
the N to the one third funnel, because,
N^(1/3)路漏斗
now, why do I use one third?
那么 为什么是1/3？
Well, because of this three.
因为这里是3
OK, in order to use the N to the one third funnel,
为了能使用这N^(1/3)路漏斗
I need to guarantee that the total number of elements
我需要确保元素的个数
that I'm merging is at least the cube of this number, K^3.
是K的立方 K^3
The cube of this number is N.
然后K^3等于N
That's exactly how many elements I have in total.
这正是我们的元素总数
OK, so this is exactly what I can apply the funnel.
而我正是要这样子来使用漏斗
It's going to require that I have it least K^3 elements,
它要求我至少有K^3个元素
so that I can only use an N to the one third funnel.
这样我才能够用N^(1/3)路漏斗
I mean, if it didn't have this requirement,
我的意思是 如果没有这个条件
I could just say, well, I have N lists each of size one.
我甚至可以说 我有N个大小为1的序列
OK, that's clearly not going to work very well for our merger,
但那对于我们的归并显然行不通
I mean, intuitively because this plus K will kill you.
因为很明显 这个+K会害死你的
That will be a plus N which is way too big.
因为它会变成+N 那就太大了
But we can use an N to the one third funnel,
我们用N^(1/3)路漏斗就好了
and this is how we would sort.
这样就能排序了
So, let's analyze this algorithm.
那么 来分析一下这个算法吧
Hopefully, it will give the sorting bound
顺利的话 它会得到那个排序的边界
if I did everything correctly.
如果我没有失误的话
OK, this is pretty easy.
其实别的都好办
The only thing that makes this messy as
只有一件事很费劲
I have to write the sorting bound over and over.
就是重复写这个排序边界很累啊
OK, this is the cost of the merge.
这是归并的花费
So that's at the root.
这是根节点的花费
But K^3 in this case is N.
而K^3在这里就是N
So at the root of the recursion,
所以在递归的根节点上
let me write the recurrence first. Sorry.
我先把递归式写一下 不好意思
So, we have memory transfers on n elements is N to the one third.
N个元素对应的内存传输量就是N^(1/3)
Let me get this right.
看一眼
Yeah, N to the one third recursions, each of size N to the two thirds
N^(1/3)乘以MT(N^(2/3))
OK, plus this time, except K^3 is N.
加上——这里K^3等于N
So, this is plus N over B, log base M over B of N over B
所以这就是(N/B)log_(M/B)(N/B)
plus cubed root of M.
加上N^(1/3)
This is additive plus K term.
就是那个K
OK, so that's my recurrence.
这个就是递归式了
The base case will be the usual.
基准情形和以前一样
MT is some constant times M is order M over B.
MT(cM)=O(M/B)（c为常数）
So, we sort of know what we should get here.
那写到这一步 我们应该知道...
Well, not really.
呃 也不全是啦
So, in all the previous recurrence is,
在以前的递归式里面
we have the same costs at every level,
我们每层的花费都是一样的
and that's where we got our log factor.
这就是我们log项的由来
Now, we already have a log factor,
现在我们已经有了一个log项
so we better not get another one.
所以 最好不要再来log项了
Right, this is the bound we want to prove.
这就是我们想要得到的边界
So, let me cheat here for a second.
我来偷看下秘籍
All right, indeed. You may already be wondering,
嘿嘿 找到了 你们可能会想
this N to the one third seems rather large.
N^(1/3)看起来很大啊
If it's bigger than this, we are already in trouble at
如果它比前面这项还大 我们就摊上大事了
the very top level of the recursion.
递归一两步就悲剧了
So, I claim that that's OK.
所以我说 大丈夫 萌大奶
Let's look at N to the one third.
我们来看看这个N^(1/3)
OK, there is a base case here which covers all values of N that are,
这个基准情形涵盖了所有的可能的N值
at most, some constant times M.
N最大不超过常数倍的M
So, if I'm in this case, I know that N is at least as big
那么在基准情形下 我知道N的值
as the cache up to some constant.
至少和缓存M一样大 取决于常数c的选择
Now the cache is it least B^2, we've assumed.
现在 我们设缓存的大小至少是B^2
And you can do this with B to
如果你想更严谨一些
the one plus epsilon if you're more careful.
你也可以写成B^(1+ε)
So, N is at least B^2, OK?
那么N至少是B^2
And then, I always have trouble with these.
呃 我老是把自己说懵了
So this means that N divided by B is omega root N.
这就是说N/B等于Ω(√N)
OK, there's many things you could say here,
不管你信不信
and only one of them is right. So, why?
反正真相只有一个 那么为什么是这样？
So this says that the square root of N is at least B,
这是说√N大于等于B
and so N divided by B is at most N divided by square root of N.
那么N/B大于等于N/√N
So that's at least the square root of N if you check that all out.
这就等于√N
I'm going to go through this arithmetic relatively quickly
我速度把这个式子算一遍
because it's tedious but necessary.
因为这很简单 但又不可或缺
OK, the square root of N is strictly bigger than cubed root of N.
√N显然是大于³√N的
OK, so that means that N over B
这就是说N/B
is strictly bigger than N to the one third.
严格大于N^(1/3)
Here we have N over B times something that's bigger than one.
而这里 我们用N/B乘以一个大于1的东西
So this term definitely dominates this term in this case.
所以这项严格大于后面的这项
As long as I'm not in the base case,
只要我还没算到基本情况
I know N is at least order M.
我就知道N至少是M阶的
This term disappears from my recurrence.
所以 这一项就从我的递归中消失了
OK, so, good. That was a bit close.
呼~ 好了 就快算出来了
Now, what we want to get is this running time overall.
我们想要在全局获得这个运行时间
So, the recursive cost better be small,
所以递归的花费最好小一点
better be less than the constant factor increase over this.
最好比这一项的常数倍要小
So, let's write the recurrence.
现在来把递归画一下
So, we get N over B, log base M over B, n over B at the root.
在根节点 数据大小是(N/B)*log_(M/B)(N/B)
Then, we split into a lot of subproblems,
然后分成很多个子问题
N to the one third subproblems here,
一共N^(1/3)个子问题
and each one costs essentially this
每个的花费都是上面这个
but with N replaced by N to the two thirds.
d但要把其中的N变成N^(2/3)
OK, so N to the two thirds log base M over B,
这就是(N^(2/3)/B)*log_(M/B)(N^(2/3)/B)
oops I forgot to divide it by B out here,
这里忘记除B了
of N to the two thirds divided by B.
就是(N^(2/3)/B)log(M/B)(N^(2/3)/B)
That's the cost of one of these nodes, there's a bunch of them
这就是一个节点的花费 而这里有一行节点
N to the one third of them. What should they add up to?
一共是N^(1/3)个节点 它们的和是多少？
Well, there is N to the one third,
数量是N^(1/3)
and there's an N to the two thirds here that multiplies out to N.
这里还有一个N^(2/3) 乘在一起就是N
So, we get N over B. This looks bad.
我们就得到了N/B——这看起来不妙啊
This looks the same.
还是那熊样啊
And we don't want to lose another log factor.
我可不想再失去一个log项了
But the good news is we have two thirds in here.
不过好在我们这个指数是2/3
OK, this is what we get in total at this level.
这就是我们在这一层得到的和
It looks like the sorting bound,
看起来跟排序的边界差不多
but in the log there's still a two thirds.
不过在log项里还有一个2/3
Now, a power of two thirds and a log
log项里的2/3指数项
comes out as a multiple of two thirds.
可以提到前面来
So, this is in fact two thirds times N over B,
所以这就是2/3乘以N/B
log base M over B of N over B, the sorting bound.
乘以log_(M/B)(N/B) 也就是排序边界
So, this is two thirds of the sorting bound.
所以这就是排序边界的2/3
And this is the sorting bound, one times the sorting bound.
而在根节点是1乘以排序边界
So, it's going down geometrically, yea!
所以这是从几何级数上变少了 哦也~~
OK, I'm not going to prove it, but it's true.
我是不想证明它了 反正它就是对的
This went down by a factor of two thirds.
这一层乘了一个2/3
The next one will also go down by a factor of two thirds by induction.
下一层又乘了一个2/3 以此类推
OK, if you prove it at one level,
所以如果你在一层证明了
it should be true at all of them.
那在所有层就都是这样
And I'm going to skip the details there.
具体细节我就先跳过
So, we could check the leaf level just to make sure.
我们可以检查一下叶节点 只是为了确定一下
That's always a good sanity check.
这是个明智的选择
At the leaves, we know our cost is M over B.
在叶节点上 我们的花费是M/B
OK, and how many leaves are there?
叶子节点有多少个？
Just like before, in some sense, we have N/M leaves.
就像以前一样 我们有N/M个叶子
OK, so in fact the total cost at the bottom is N over B.
所以最底层的花费应该是N/B
And it turns out that that's what you get.
而且这就是你得到的
So, you essentially, it looks funny,
看起来挺有意思
because you'd think that this
因为你可能会以为
would actually be smaller than this at some intuitive level.
这个会比下面这个小 感觉上是这样
It's not. In fact, what's happening is
其实不是 事实是
you have this N over B times this log thing,
在这里是N/B乘以这个log项
whatever the log thing is. We don't care too much.
不管log后面是什么了 那不重要
Let's just call it log.
就叫它log好了
What you are taking at the next level is two thirds times that log.
我们在下一层就是用2/3乘以这个log
And at the next level, it's four ninths times that log and so on.
再下一层 就是4/9乘以log 以此类推
So, it's geometrically decreasing until the log gets down to one.
这个log项不断减小 直到log项减小到1
And then you stop the recursion.
然后就停止递归
And that's what you get N over B here with no log.
这就是为什么这个N/B后面没有log
So, what you're doing is decreasing the log,
所以你做的其实只是减小log项
not the N over B stuff.
而N/B岿然不动
The two thirds should really be over here.
2/3应该是在指数位置上
In fact, the number of levels here is log, log N.
这个树的层数应该是log(log N)
It's the number of times you have to divide a log by three
这是你把这个log项用3/2除到1
halves before you get down to one, OK?
所需要的次数
So, we don't actually need that.
我们用不着那个
We don't care how many levels are
我们不关心到底有多少层
because it's geometrically decreasing.
因为它是几何级数减少的
It could be infinitely many levels.
它还可能有无限层呢
It's geometrically decreasing, and we get this as our running time.
反正是几何级数减少 而这个就是我们得到的运行时间
MT of N is the sorting bound for funnel sort.
MT(N)等于漏斗排序边界
So, this is great.
这个太帅了
As long as we can get a funnel that merges this quickly,
只要我们能找到一个能够快速归并的漏斗
we get a sorting algorithm that sorts as fast as it possibly can.
我们就能找到一个尽可能快的算法来排序
I didn't write that. But on the board, this is asymptotically optimal
我虽然没写出来 但这是目前黑板上的一个渐进最优解了
Even if you knew what B and M were,
即使你知道B和M是多少
this is the best that you could hope to do.
这也是你所能取得的最优解了
And here, we are doing it no matter what, B and M are. Good.
而我们现在做的 就是B和M无关的算法
Get ready for the funnel.
准备迎接漏斗的洗礼吧
The funnel will be another recursion.
漏斗就是另一个递归了
So, this is a recursive algorithm in a recursive algorithm.
所以 这是递归中的递归
It's another divide and conquer,
是另一种分治法
kind of like the static search trees
有点像是静态搜索树
we saw at the beginning of this lecture.
就是我们这门课一开始讲的
So, these all tie together.
它们都是互相关联的
All right, the K funnel, so, I'm calling it K funnel
好的 K漏斗 之所以叫K漏斗
because I want to think of it at some recursive level,
因为我想从广义的递归层面来考虑它
not just N to the one third.
而不只是N^(1/3)路递归
OK, we're going to recursively use,
但实际上 我们是打算
in fact, the square root of K funnel.
递归地使用√K漏斗
So, here's, and I need to achieve that bound.
我们的目的是取得那个复杂度边界
So, the recursion is like the static search tree,
这个递归就像是静态搜索树
and a little bit hard to draw on one board,
画在黑板上可能有些困难
but here we go.
但还是来一发吧
So, we have a square root of K funnel.
这就是我们的√K漏斗
Recursively, we have a buffer up here.
这上面有一个缓冲区
This is called the output buffer,
叫做输出缓冲区
and it has size K^3, and just for kicks,
大小是K^3 为了显得真实一些
let's suppose it that filled up a little bit.
我们假设它里面已经装进了一些奇怪的东西
And, we have some more buffers.
然后 下面是更多的缓冲区
And, let's suppose they've been filled up by different amounts.
假设它们都被装进了一些不同数量的东西
And each of these has size K to the three halves, of course.
每个的大小都是K^(3/2)
Halves, these are called buffers, let's say,
这些都叫缓冲区
with the intermediate buffers. And, then hanging off of them,
或者叫中间缓冲区 它们下面挂着的是
we have more funnels, the square root of K funnel here,
更多的漏斗 这有一个√K漏斗
and a square root of K funnel here,
这也有一个√K漏斗
one for each buffer,
每个缓冲区都有一个
one for each child of this funnel.
每个都是上面这个漏斗的子漏斗
OK, and then hanging off of these funnels are the input arrays.
然后在这些漏斗下面是输入序列
OK, I'm not going to draw all K of them,
我可没傻到把K个全画出来
but there are K input arrays,
不过这里的确有K个输入序列
input lists let's call them down at the bottom.
输入的数组 它们在最底层
OK, so the idea is we are going to merge bottom-up in this picture.
我们要做的就是自底向上做归并
We start with our K input
我们从K个输入序列开始
arrays of total size at least K^3.
它们总的大小至少是K^3
That's what we're assuming we have up here.
这是我们上面提到的前提假设
We are clustering them into groups of size square root of K,
我们把这些序列分成√K大小的组
so, the square root of K groups,
这样每个组有√K个序列
throw each of them into a square root of K funnel that
每个序列把数据输入它所在的√k漏斗中
recursively merges those square root of K lists.
然后递归地归并这些序列
The output of those funnels we are putting into
这些漏斗的输出放在一个缓冲区里
a buffer to sort of accumulate what the answer should be.
输出结果会暂时积累在缓冲区里
These buffers have size exactly K to the three halves,
这些缓冲区大小恰好为K^(3/2)
which might not be perfect because we know that on average,
虽然这可能不是最好的选择 这是因为...
there should be K to the three halves elements in each of these
平均来说 这下面每个漏斗对应K^(3/2)个元素
because there's K^3 total,
因为总数是K^3
and the square root of K groups.
组的个数是√K个
So, it should be K^3 divided by the square root of K,
所以应该是K^3除以√K
which is K to the three halves on average.
所以平均来说 应该每个都是K^(3/2)
But some of these will be bigger.
但有些缓冲区会比较大
Some of them will be smaller. I've drawn it here.
有些小一点 我在这画出来了
Some of them had emptied a bit more depending on how you merge things.
有些缓冲区空出了一部分 这取决于你是怎么归并的
But on average, these will all fill at the same time.
但平均来说 中间的缓冲区应该是同时装满的
And then, we plug them into a square root of K funnel,
然后 我们把它们放进这一个√K漏斗里
and that we get the output of size K^3.
然后我们就得到了大小为K^3的输出
So that is, roughly, what it should have happened.
那么 大概就是这么个情况
OK, but in fact, some of these might fill first,
事实上 有的缓冲区已被填充
and we have to do some merging in order to empty a buffer,
我们就需要做一些归并来腾出地方
make room for more stuff coming up.
为下面的数据做准备
That's the picture.
这个图就说这么多
Now, before I actually tell you what the algorithm is,
在我讲这个算法之前
or analyze the algorithm,
或者说分析算法之前
let's first just think about space,
我们先来考虑一下空间问题
a very simple warm-up analysis.
一个很简单的热身分析
So, let's look at the space excluding the inputs and outputs,
我们先不考虑输入输出
those buffers.
不管那些缓冲大小
OK, why do I want to exclude input and output buffers?
为什么我要忽略输入输出的缓冲大小呢？
Well, because I only want to count each buffer once,
因为每个缓冲区我只算一次
and this buffer is actually the input to this one
而这个缓冲区既是上面这个漏斗的输入
and the output to this one.
也是下面这个漏斗的输出
So, in order to recursively count all the buffers exactly once,
为了要递归地计算缓冲大小 而且每个缓冲区只算一遍
I'm only going to count these middle buffers.
我就只算中间的缓冲区就好了
And then separately,
除此之外
I'm going to have to think of the overall output and input buffers.
我还必须计算总的输入、输出
But those are sort of given.
不过它们算是已知的了
I mean, I need K^3 for the output.
输出是K^3
I need K^3 for the input. So ignore those overall.
输入也是K^3 所以 还是忽略它们吧
And that if I count the middle buffers recursively,
因为如果我用递归地计算中间的缓冲区
I'll get all the buffers.
我就得到总的缓冲大小了
So, then we get a very simple recurrence for space.
那么 我们得出一条简单的空间递归式
S of K is roughly square root of K plus
S(K)就等于(√K+1)
one times S of square root of K plus order K^2,
乘以S(√K) 再加上O(K^2)
K^2 because we have the square root of K of these buffers,
K^2是因为我们在中间有√K个缓冲区
each of size K to the three halves.
每个大小都是K^(3/2)
Work that out, does that sound right?
算一下 嗯？ 我好像刚刚说错了什么
That sounds an awful lot like K^3, but maybe,
听起来像是K^3 有种不祥的感觉啊…
all right. I don't know, that's right.
不管了 反正翻译会修正的
It's K to the three halves times the square root of K,
就是K^(3/2)乘以√K
which is K to the three halves plus a half,
就是K^(3/2+1/2)
which is K to the four halves, which is K^2.
K^(4/2) 也就是K^2
Phew, OK, good.
很好喵
I'm just bad with my arithmetic here.
我的数学没学好
OK, so K^2 total buffering here.
所以中间的缓冲大小为K^2
You add them up for each level, each recursion,
然后你再把递归每一层的大小加起来
and the plus one here is to take into account the top guy,
这里+1是指上面的漏斗
the square root of K bottom guys, so the square root of K plus one.
√K是指它下面的漏斗 所以递归项里是√K+1个
If this were, well, let me just draw the recurrence tree.
好吧 我还是画一下递归树
There's many ways you could solve this recurrence.
我们可以用很多方法来解这个递归式
A natural one is instead of looking at K,
你可以不用K来算
you look at log K, because here at log K is getting divided by two.
你可以算log K 这样这里就变½ log K了
I just going to draw the recursion trees,
我只要画一下递归树
so you can see the intuition.
你们就明白了
But if you are going to solve it,
不过如果你要解这条式
you should probably take the logs, substitute by log.
你可以取个log 用log项的替代法
So, we have the square root of K plus one branching factor.
所以我们的分支数是√K+1
And then, the problem is size square root of K,
然后分支大小是√K
so this is going to be K, I believe, for each of these.
所以每个分支的花费就是O(K)了
This is square root of K squared is the cost of these levels.
也就是O(√(K^2))
And, you keep going.
然后继续
I don't particularly care what the bottom looks like
我不管递归最底层的情况
because at the top we have K^2.
但因为最顶层我们有K^2
That we have K times root K plus one cost at the next level.
而它的下一层的花费是K(√K+1)
This is K to the three halves plus K.
也就是K^(3/2)+K
OK, so we go from K^2 to K to the three halves plus K.
我们从K^2降到了K^(3/2)+K
This is a super-geometric.
这比几何级数还多
It's like an exponential geometric decrease.
差不多是指数级别的下降
This is decreasing really fast. So, it's order K^2.
它的下降的速度相当快 所以总的来说是K^2阶
That's my hand-waving argument.
这是个令人愉悦的消息
OK, so the cost is basically the size of the buffers at the top level,
那么缓存的花费基本都集中在最顶层
the total space.
我是说总的花费
We're going to need this.
我们会用到这个式子
It's actually theta K^2 because
其实应该是Θ(K^2)
I have a theta K^2 here.
因为上面就是Θ(K^2)
We are going to be this in order to analyze the time.
分析时间复杂度的时候会用到这个
That's why it mentioned it.
这就是我讲这个的原因
It's not just a good feeling that the space is not too big.
它的意义不只是说“哎哟不错喔 空间用不多”
In fact, the funnel is a lot smaller than a total input size.
实际上 这个漏斗的大小远小于输入的大小
The input size is K^3. But that's not so crucial.
输入的大小可是K^3 不过这不是最关键的
What's crucial is that it's K^2, and we'll use that in the analysis.
关键是这个K^2 我们在分析中会用到
OK, naturally, this thing is laid out recursively.
那么 整个漏斗就是这么递归地分布的
You recursively store the funnel, top funnel.
你递归地储存这些漏斗
Then, for example, you write out each buffer
比如这里 你把所有的缓冲区
as a consecutive array, in this case.
存储成一个连续的数组
There's no recursion there.
这里还没有递归
So just write them all out one by one.
就是一个接一个输出就好了
Don't interleave them or anything.
别让它们重叠了
Store them in order.
按顺序把他们放好
And that, you write out recursively these funnels,
然后你再递归地存储这些漏斗
the bottom funnels.
下面这层漏斗
OK, any way you do it recursively,
不管你用什么方法递归
as long as each funnel remains a consecutive chunk of memory,
只要每个漏斗用的是一块连续的内存
each buffer remains a consecutive chuck of memory,
只要每个缓冲区用的是一块连续的内存
the time analysis that we are about to do will work.
我们下面要做的时间分析就会派上用场
OK, let me actually give you the algorithm that we're analyzing.
我还是把要分析的算法写出来吧
In order to make the funnel go, what we do is say,
为了让这个漏斗能够运作 我们要做的是
initially, all the buffers are empty.
在初始化时 这些缓冲区都清空
Everything is at the bottom.
所有输入序列都在底下
And what we are going to do is, say, fill the root buffer.
而我们的目标是 填满根部的缓冲区（输出缓冲）
Fill this one. And, that's a recursive algorithm,
把它填满 而这又是另一个递归算法了
which I'll define in a second, how to fill a buffer.
我马上就会讲要怎么填满缓冲区
Once it's filled, that means everything has been pulled up,
一旦它被填满 就意味着所有的东西都输出了
and then it's merged.
归并就完成了
OK, so that's how we get started.
这就是我们的第一步
So, merge means, the merge algorithm is fill the topmost buffer,
归并就是要填满最上面的缓冲区
the topmost output buffer.
顶端输出缓冲区
OK, and now, here's how you fill a buffer.
然后我们来讲怎么填满一个缓冲区
So, in general, if you expand out this recursion all the way,
一般来说 如果你把这个递归过程全部展开
in the base case, I didn't mention you sort of get a little node there.
在底层的实现里 其实有一个细节 这里是有个节点的
So, if you look at an arbitrary buffer
也就是说 你在这个图里
in this picture that you want to fill,
任意取一个缓冲区
so this one's empty and you want to fill it,
这个缓冲区是空的 你要填满它
then immediately below it will be a vertex who has two children,
而它下面会有一个节点 这个节点连着两个子缓冲
two other buffers. OK, maybe they look like this.
另外两个缓冲区 就像这样连着
You have no idea how big they are, except they are the same size.
你只知道它们一样大 但不知道究竟有多大
It could be a lot smaller than this one,
它可能比上面的小很多
a lot bigger, we don't know.
或者大很多 我们都不知道
But in the end, you do get a binary structure out of this
不过在最底层 你得到的是一个二分的结构
just like we did with the binary search tree at the beginning.
就像我们最开始讲过的二分搜索树一样
So, how do we fill this buffer?
那么我们如何填充缓冲区？
Well, we just merge these two child buffers as long as we can.
我们只要对这两个子缓冲区做归并就可以了
So, we merge the two children buffers
那么 只要两个子缓冲非空
as long as they are both non-empty.
我们就把它们归并起来
So, in general, the invariant will be that this buffer,
所以 有一件事是不变的
let me write down a sentence.
我还是写一下吧
As long as a buffer is non-empty,
只要有一个缓冲区是非空的
or whatever is in that buffer and hasn't been used already
或者说 缓冲区里还有没用到的东西
it's a prefix of the merged output of the entire subtree beneath it.
那些东西就是在这个缓冲下面的子树的归并输出
OK, so this is a partially merged subsequence of everything down here.
这个缓冲区里装的是它下面的子树的归并结果
This is a partially merged subsequence of everything down here.
这个缓冲区里也是它下面的归并结果
I can just merge element by element off the top,
我可以从顶部开始归并这俩缓冲的元素
and that will give me outputs to put there
得到的输出就放在上面的缓冲区
until one of them gets emptied.
直到有一个缓冲区被清空了
And, we have no idea which one will empty first
我们也不知道哪个会先清空
just because it depends on the order.
因为这和实际数据的顺序有关
OK, whenever one of them empties, we recursively fill it,
当其中一个被清空了 我们就递归地将其填满
and that's it. That's the algorithm.
就是这样了 这就是算法
Whenever one empties --
当有一个缓冲区被清空了——
-- we recursively fill it.
就开始递归地填充
And at the base case at the leaves,
基准情形里 就是在叶节点里
there's sort of nothing to do.
我们不需要做什么别的
I believe you just sort of directly read from an input list.
只要把输入的序列读进来缓存就好
So, at the very bottom,
在最下面的地方
you have some nodes here
会有一些节点
that's trying to merge between these two,
它会归并这两个输入序列
that's just a straightforward merge between two lists.
就是两个序列之间的最直接的归并
We know how to do that with two parallel scans.
我们都知道 它是用两个并行扫描来完成的
So, in fact, we can merge the entire thing here
所以 我们可以一步步把整个序列都归并了
and just spit it out to the buffer.
然后扔到缓冲区里
Well, it depends how big the buffer is.
好吧 这也取决于缓冲区的大小
We can only merge it until the buffer fills.
我们只能归并到缓冲区满了为止
Whenever a buffer is full,
一旦缓冲区被填满了
we stop and we pop up the recursive layers.
我们就停下来 把结果递归地向上传
OK, so we keep doing this merge until
所以 我们就一直这么做归并
the buffer we are trying to fill fills,
直到缓冲区填满了为止
and that we stop, pop up.
然后停下来 向上一级传结果
OK, that's the algorithm for merging.
这就是归并的算法了
Now, we just have to analyze the algorithm.
现在 我们还需要分析一下这个算法
It's actually not too hard, but it's a pretty clever analysis.
这并不是很困难 不过这是个很巧妙的分析
And, to top it off, it's an amortization,
更重要的是 这是个平摊分析
your favorite. OK, so we get one last practice
这是你们的最爱啊 好的 最后我们来做一次
at amortized analysis in the context of cache oblivious algorithms.
关于缓参无关的平摊分析
So, this is going to be a bit sophisticated.
这可能有一点点复杂
We are going to combine all the ideas we've seen.
我们要把见过的所有东西融会贯通
The main analysis idea we've seen is that
这个分析主要的思想是
we are doing this recursion in the construction,
我们在递归的构造这个K漏斗
and if we imagine, we take our K funnel,
想象一下 如果我们把K漏斗
we split it in the middle level,
从中间分开
make a whole bunch of square root of K funnels,
变成许许多多的√K漏斗
and so on, and then we cut those in the middle level,
然后反复 然后我们继续在中间分开
get fourth root of K funnels, and so on, and so on,
得到开四次方的K漏斗 然后反复下去
at some point the funnel we look at fits in cache.
直到漏斗的大小正好能匹配上缓存
OK, before we said if it's in a block.
以前我们会说它跟块匹配
Now, we're going to say that at some point,
而现在是分割到一定程度时
one of these funnels will fit in cache.
这些漏斗都正好与缓存匹配
Each of the funnels at that recursive level of detail will fit in cache.
在这一层递归的每一个漏斗都和缓存匹配
We are going to analyze that level.
我们就来分析这一层
We'll call that level J.
我们管它叫J级
So, consider the first recursive level of detail,
考虑第一个满足以下条件的递归层
and I'll call it J, at which every J funnel we have fits,
我们称之为J级 这时每个J漏斗都与缓存匹配
let's say, not only does it fit in cache,
而且不是简单地和缓存相匹配
but four of them fit in cache.
而是四个漏斗匹配一个缓存
It fits in one quarter of the cache.
也就是一个漏斗匹配四分之一个缓存
OK, we need to leave some cache extra for doing other things.
我们还需要给缓存留点地方去做别的事
But I want to make sure that the J funnel fits.
不过我想要保证J漏斗跟缓存匹配
OK, now what does that mean? Well, we've analyzed space.
这是什么意思？ 我们已经分析了空间的问题
We know that the space of a J funnel is about J^2,
我们知道一个J漏斗所占的空间大约是J^2
some constant times J^2. We'll call it c times J^2.
某个常数乘以J^2 也就是cJ^2
OK, so this is saying that C times J^2 is at most M over 4,
这就是说cJ^2 ≤ M/4
one quarter of the cache.
就是四分之一的缓存
OK, that means a J funnel that happens at the size
这就是说一个J漏斗的大小应该
fits in the quarter of the cache.
正好能装进四分之一个缓存里
OK, at some point in the recursion,
所以 在递归的某一步
we'll have this big tree of J funnels,
递归树里会出现符合条件的J漏斗
with all sorts of buffers in between them,
它们的缓冲大小不一
and each of the J funnels will fit.
但每个J漏斗都和缓存相匹配
So, let's think about one of those J funnels.
我们来考虑一下其中的一个J漏斗
Suppose J is like the square root of K.
假设J就是√K
So, this is the picture because otherwise I have to draw a bigger one.
就是用这幅图吧 要不然就就要画一幅更大的了
So, suppose this is a J funnel.
假设这就是一个J漏斗
It has a bunch of input buffers, has one output buffer.
它有一堆输入缓冲区 还有一个输出缓冲区
So, we just want to think about how the J funnel executes.
我们要考虑的就是J漏斗的工作方式
And, for a long time, as long as these buffers are all full,
在很长一段时间内 只要这些缓冲区是满的
this is just a merger.
它的作用就是一个归并器
It's doing something recursively, but we don't really care.
它会做一些递归的步骤 但我们不关心那些
As soon as this whole thing swaps in,
只要这整个递归器换入到内存里时
and actually, I should be drawing this, as soon as the funnel,
我其实把这一整块都圈起来 就是这个漏斗
the output buffer, and the input buffer swap in,
和它的输入输出缓冲区都换入到内存里
in other words, you bring all those blocks in,
换而言之 所有有关的块都在内存里
you can just merge, and you can go on your merry
你就可以尽情的进行归并
way merging until something empties or you fill the output.
直到输入缓冲区空了 或者输出缓冲区满了
So, let's analyze that.
我们就来分析这种情况
Suppose everything is in memory, because we know it fits.
假设所有东西都在内存里 因为我们知道它跟内存匹配
OK, well I have to be a little bit careful.
嗯 我还是得小心一点
The input buffers are actually pretty big in total size
因为输入缓冲区的总大小还挺大的
because the total size is K to the three halves here
因为输入是K^(3/2)
versus K to the one half.
输出是K^(1/2)
Actually, this is of size K. Let me draw a general picture.
这个的大小其实是K 我来画一个总体的图
We have a J funnel,
这是一个J漏斗
because otherwise the arithmetic is going to get messy.
这样算数好算一点
We have a J funnel. Its size is C times J^2,
这是一个J漏斗 大小是CJ^2
we're supposing.
应该是这样
The number of inputs is J, and the size of them is pretty big.
输入的数量是J 它们的大小都很大
Where did we define that? We have a K funnel.
前面我们是怎么说的？ 这是一个K漏斗
The total input size is K^3.
总输入为K^3
So, the total input size here would be J^3.
所以这个输入的大小应该是J^3
We can't afford to put all that in cache.
我们不可能把所有东西都放入缓存
That's an extra factor of J.
因为它多了J因子
But, we can afford to one block per input.
但我们可以做到每个输入一个块
And for merging, that's all we need.
对于归并来说 这就足够了
I claim that I can fit the first block of each of these input
对于每个输入序列 它的第一个块可以
arrays in cache at the same time along with the J funnel.
跟整个J漏斗一起装进内存里
And so, for that duration, as long as all of that is in cache,
在这个过程中 只要这些东西都在缓存里
this thing can merge at full speed
这个归并就可以火力全开
just like we were doing parallel scans.
就像我们做并行扫描一样
You use up all the blocks down here, and one of them empties.
把这些块都用光了之后 肯定有一块是空了的
You go to the next block in the input buffer and so on,
你就到它对应的输入缓冲里找下一个块
just like the normal merge analysis of parallel arrays,
就像普通的并行归并分析一样
at this point we assume that everything here is fitting in cache.
而这时 我们假设这些东西都能和缓存匹配
So, it's just like before. Of course, in fact,
就像以前讲过的一样 当然了
it's recursive but we are analyzing it at this level.
这其实是递归执行的 但我们就只分析这一层的事
OK, I need to prove that you can fit one block per input.
好的 我要证明你可以容纳每个输入序列存一个块
It's not hard. It's just computation.
这也不难 只是计算量的问题
And, it's basically the way that these funnels were designed
而基本上 这漏斗的设计方式
was so that you could fit one block per input buffer.
就是为了能容纳每个输入序列存一个块
And, here's the argument.
下面就是证明
So, the claim is you can also fit one memory block
我们的目标是证明 缓存可以容纳
in the cache per input buffer.
一个输入序列存一个块
So, this is in addition to one J funnel.
这是说除了要存一个J漏斗外
You could also fit one block for each of its input buffers.
你也可以容纳一个输入序列存一个块
OK, this is of the J funnel.
这里对应的是J漏斗
It's not any funnel because bigger funnels are way too big.
不是所有漏斗都行 因为大的漏斗太大了
OK, so here's how we prove that.
下面就是证明了
J^2 is at most a quarter M.
J^2小于等于(1/4)M
That's what we assumed here, actually CJ^2.
这就是我们这里说过的 应该说是cJ^2
I'm not going to bother with the C
我就不在c上多花时间了
because that's going to make my life even harder.
因为这已经够我受的了
OK, I think this is even a weaker constraint.
嗯 这已经是个很弱的约束条件了
So, the size of our funnel proves about J^2.
我们证明过漏斗大小大约是J^2
That's at most a quarter of the cache.
然后它最多是1/4个缓存
That implies that J, if we take square roots of both sides,
这意味着 如果对两边开平方
is at most a half square root of M.
得到J小于等于(1/2)√M
OK, also, we know that B is at most square root of M
我们还知道B小于等于√M
because M is at least B squared.
因为M大于等于B^2
So, we put these together,
所以我们把它们放在一起
and we get J times B is at most a half M.
得到了J*B小于等于(1/2)M
Now I claim that what we are asking for here is J times B
我们之所以要算J乘B
because in a J funnel, there are J input arrays.
是因为在J漏斗里 有J个输入序列
And so, if you want one block each, that costs a space of B each.
如果要每个输入存一个块 那每次就要B的空间
So, for each input buffer we have one block of size B,
对于每个输入序列 它都有B大小的块
and the claim is that that whole thing fits in half the cache.
这条式子说明了 它的总大小跟缓存大小的一半匹配
And, we've only used a quarter of the cache.
之前我们只用了四分之一的缓存
So in total, we use three quarters of the cache
所以 总计就用了四分之三的缓存
and that's all we'll use.
我就是我们所有的花费
OK, so that's good news.
这听起来不错
We can also fit one more block to the output.
因为我们还能给输出留一个块
Not too big a deal.
毫无压力
So now, as long as this J funnel is running,
只要J漏斗还在工作
if it's all in cache, all is well.
只要所有东西都在缓存里 就妥妥的了
What does that mean? Let me first analyze how long
这意味着什么？ 我们先来分析一下
it takes for us to swap in this funnel.
换入到内存的时间花费是多少
OK, so how long does it take for us to read all the stuff
把整个J漏斗 还有一输入一块都读进来
in a J funnel and one block per input buffer?
需要花费多少时间？
That's what it would take to get started.
我们来研究一下
So, this is swapping in a J funnel,
好的 这是J漏斗的换入操作
which means reading the J funnel in its entirety,
也就是把整个J漏斗
and reading one block per input buffer.
还有一个输入一个块读入内存
OK, the cost of the swap in is pretty natural.
换入操作的花费很好理解
The size of the buffer divided by B,
就是缓存大小除以B
because that's just sort of a linear scan to read it in,
因为读入就是线性的扫描
and we need to read one block per buffer.
我们还需要每个输入读一个块
These buffers could be all over the place because they're pretty big.
而输入缓冲的分布很散 因为它们实在太大
So, let's say we pay one memory transfer for each input buffer
所以我们设在读入一个输入序列的块之前
just to get started to read the first block.
我们需要额外一个内存传输
OK, the claim is,
这就是说
and here we need to do some more arithmetic.
这里我们要算的东西比较多
This is, at most, J^3 over B.
它小于等于J^3/B
OK, why is it, at most, J^3 over B?
为什么它不超过J^3/B？
Well, this was the first level at which things fit in cache.
因为它是缓存能装下的第一个层
That means the next level bigger, which is J^2,
这就是说比它大的那层 就是J^2那层
which has size J^4, should be bigger than cache.
它的大小是J^4 缓存已经装不下了
Otherwise we would have stopped then.
不然我们就在那一层停下了
OK, so this is just more arithmetic.
这其实就是多算几步
You can either believe me or follow the arithmetic.
你可以选择相信我或者是算一下
We know that J^4 is at least M. So, this means that,
我们知道J^4≥M 那这就意味着
and we know that M is at least B^2.
而M≥B^2
Therefore, J^2, instead of J^4,
因此 J^2而不是J^4
we take the square root of both sides, J^2 is at least B.
我们对等式两边开平方 得到J^2≥B
OK, so certainly J^2 over B is at most J^3 over B.
那么 J^2/B肯定是小于J^3/B
But also J is at most J^3 over B because J^2 is at least B.
我们还能得出J小于等于J^3 因为J^2≥B
Hopefully that should be clear. That's just algebra.
这应该清楚了 这就是算数而已
OK, so we're not going to use this bound
我们不会用这个边界
because that's kind of complicated.
因为它挺复杂的
We're just going to say, well,
我们只是说
it causes J^3 over B to get swapped in.
换入操作的花费就是J^3/B
Now, why is J^3 over B a good thing?
为什么J^3/B是个好东西？
Because we know the total size of inputs to the J funnel is J^3.
因为我们知道输入的总大小是J^3
So, to read all of the inputs to the J funnel takes J^3 over B.
所以 把J漏斗的输入都读进来 花费就是J^3/B
So, this is really just a linear extra cost to get the
也就是说 这只是多用了一点线性的花费
whole thing swapped in. It sounds good.
就完成了整个换入操作 不错嘛
To do the merging would also cost J^3 over B.
做归并的花费也是J^3/B
So, the swap-in causes J^3 over B
那么 换入操作是J^3/B
To merge all these J^3 elements.
而要归并J^3个元素
if they were all there in the inputs,
如果它们都在缓存里放好了
it would take J^3 over B because once everything is there,
它的花费就是J^3/B 因为如果它们都放好了
you're merging at full speed,
你的归并就是全速前进的
one per B items per memory transfer on average.
平均一次传输可以处理B个元素
OK, the problem is you're going to swap out,
问题是你还要换出
which you may have imagined.
你们可能想到了
As soon as one of your input buffers empties,
当你的某个输入缓冲区清空了的时候
let's say this one's almost gone, as soon as it empties,
比如说这个没剩多少的 如果它空了的话
you're going to totally obliterate that funnel and swap
你就得把整个漏斗清空
in this one in order to merge all the stuff there,
然后从下面换入新的数据 把这个缓冲区填满
and fill this buffer back up.
继续执行归并直到结束
This is where the amortization comes in.
下面就该平摊分析出场了
And this is where the log factor comes in
这也是为什么会有log项的原因
because so far it we've basically paid a linear cost.
因为我们目前为止只有一点线性的花费
We are almost done.
就快搞定了
So, we charge, sorry, I'm jumping ahead of myself.
所以我们——啊 还没讲到这里呢
So, when an input buffer empties,
当一个输入缓冲区空了
we swap out.
我们执行换出操作
And we recursively fill that buffer.
然后再递归地把那个缓冲区重新填满
OK, I'm going to assume that there is absolutely no reuse,
假设我们完全没有重用原来的缓冲
that is recursive filling completely swapped everything out
这个递归把所有的东西都换出了
and I have to start from scratch for this funnel.
我就得从下面的漏斗里重新提取数据
So, when that happens, I fill this buffer,
这样的话 我就得递归地重填下下面的缓冲区
and then I come back and I say, well, I go swap it back in.
最后我再回过头来 把新的数据换入进来
So when the recursive call finishes, I swap back in.
就是说递归重填完毕后 我就执行换入操作
OK, so I recursively fill, and then I swap back in.
所以我先递归的填充 然后再换入
And, at the swapping back in costs J^3 over B.
换入的操作花费是J^3/B
I'm going to charge that cost to the elements that just got filled.
我要把这部分花费平摊到刚刚填充的那部分元素上
So this is an amortized charging argument.
所以这是一个平摊计费的问题
How many are there? It's the only question.
问题是有多少这样的元素？
It turns out, things are really good,
其实这还挺好算的
like here, for the square root of K funnel,
比如这里 对于√K漏斗
we have each buffer has size K to the three halves.
每个缓冲区的大小是K^(3/2)
OK, so this is a bit complicated.
有点绕啊
But I claim that the number of elements here
我是说 填充缓冲区的元素个数
that fill the buffer is J^3.
应该是J^3
So, if you have a J funnel,
所以对于一个J漏斗
each of the input buffers has size J^3.
每个输入缓冲区的大小都是J^3
It should be correct if you work it out.
这是根据前面的证明得出的
So, we're charging this J^3 over B cost to J^3 elements,
所以 我们对这J^3个元素的计费是J^3/B
which sounds like you're charging,
就好像 对每个元素的计费是1/B
Sounds great. That means that,
听起来不错 这就是说——
so you're thinking overall, I mean, there are N elements,
从头想一想 我有N个元素
and to each one you charge a one over B cost.
对每个元素的计费是1/B
That sounds like the total running time is N over B.
听起来好像总运行时间是N/B
It's a bit too fast for sorting.
对于排序这也太快了
We lost the log factor. So, what's going on is that
我们忘了log项了 那到底是怎么回事？
we're actually charging to one element more than once.
我们实际上对每个元素的计费不止一次
And, this is something that we don't normally do,
我们一般都不会这么做
never done it in this class, but you can do it as long as
至少以前的课上没这么做过
you bound that the number of times you charge.
不过你可以限制计费的次数
OK, and wherever you do a charging argument,
每当你做计费分析的时候
you say, well, this doesn't happen too many times
你会发现 这个其实不用算那么多次
because whenever this happens, this happens.
因为算这个的同时 那个也算了
You should prove that the thing that you're charging to,
你要证明你计费的对象
you don't charged to that thing many times.
不会被计费太多次
So here, I have a quantifiable thing that I'm charging to: elements.
这里我们就有一个计费的对象：元素
So, I'm saying that for each element that
对于每个换入到缓冲区的元素
I'm going to charge it a one over B cost.
我都向它收费1/B
How many times does one element get charged?
那对同一个元素我收费了多少次？
Well, each time it gets charged to, it's moved into a new buffer.
每次它被计费一次 它就移动到一个新的缓冲去
How many buffers could it move through?
那么它经过了多少个缓冲区？
Well, it's just going up all the time.
它一直都在从下到上移动
Merging always goes up.
归并是向上的
So, we start here and you go to the next buffer,
我们从这里开始 到下一个缓冲区
and you go to the next buffer.
然后再到下一个
The number of buffers you visit is the right log,
经过的缓冲区数目就是那个log项
it turns out. I don't know which log that is.
我也不知道是哪个log了
So, the number of charges of a one over B cost to each element
每个元素被计费的次数
is the number of buffers it visits, and that's a log factor.
就是它访问到的缓冲区数 就是一个log项
That's where we get an extra log factor on the running time.
这就是我们为什么运行时间里有log项
It is, this is the number of levels of J funnels that you can visit.
这是要访问的J漏斗的个数
So, it's log K divided by log J,
那就是log K除以log J
if I got it right. OK, and we're almost done.
应该没错 就快大功告成了
Let's wrap up a bit.
用一下上面的黑板
Just a little bit more arithmetic, unfortunately.
不幸的是还得算点东西
So, log K over log J.
那么log K/log J
Now, J^2 is like M, roughly.
J^2和M差不多
It might be square root of M. But, log J is basically log M.
J可能是√M 不过log J和log M差不多
There's some constants there.
差的只是常数因子而已
So, the number of charges here is theta, log K over log M.
所以计费的次数就是Θ(log K/log M)
we haven't seen this in amortization necessarily,
虽然这个平摊分析里不是肯定会用到
but we just need to count up total amount of charging.
但现在我们还是需要算出总的计费次数
All work gets charged to somebody,
所有的操作都要计费
except we didn't charge the very initial swapping in to everybody.
除了最开始的换入不需要计费
But, every time we do some swapping in, we charge it to someone.
不过每次执行换入操作 我们就得计费了
So, how many times does everything it charged?
那么所有的计费次数是多少
Well, there are N elements.
有N个元素
Each gets charged to a one over B cost,
每个元素收费1/B
and the number of times it gets charged is its log K over log M.
计费的次数是log K/log M
So therefore, the total cost is number of elements
所以总花费就是元素的个数
times a one over B times this log thing.
乘以1/B乘以这个log项
OK, it's actually plus K. We forgot about a plus K,
其实还有一个+K 我们忘了这个+K
but that's just to get started in the very beginning,
这是在最开始的第一步的花费
and start on all of the input lists.
用来输入所有的序列
OK, this is an amortization analysis to prove this bound.
这个平摊分析得出的这个界
Sorry, what was N here?
不好意思 这个N是什么
I assumed that I started out with K cubed elements at the bottom.
我假设过 数据是K^3个元素
The total number of elements in the bottom was K^3 theta.
最底层的元素个数为Θ(K^3)
OK, so I should have written K^3 not N.
所以我应该用K^3而不是N
This should be almost the same as this, OK, but not quite.
这两个其实差不多 不过不完全一样
This is log based M of K, and if you do a little bit of arithmetic,
这是log_M(K) 而且如果你算一下
this should be K^3 over B times log base M over B of K over B
这就是K^3/B乘以log_(M/B)(K/B)
plus K. That's what I want to prove.
再加上K 这就是我想要的
Actually there's a K^3 here instead of a K,
这个log里应该是K^3
but that's just a factor of three.
不过对于log来说 它只是个因子3而已
And this follows because we assume we are not in the base case.
接下来 因为我们假设这不是基准情形
So, K is at least M, which is at least B^2,
所以 K大于等于M 也就是大于等于B^2
and therefore K over B is omega square root of K.
那么K/B就等于Ω(√K)
OK, so K over B is basically the same as K when you put it in a log.
在log里面 K/B是和K差不多的
So here we have log base M.
这个是以M为底的log
I turned it into log base M over B. That's even worse.
我把它转为M/B 就更乱了
It doesn't matter. And, I have log of K.
不过这都无所谓 现在我有一个log K
I replaced it with K over B,
替换成K/B
but K over B is basically square root of K.
而K/B大约是√K
So in a log, that's just a factor of a half.
在log里 这就是一个1/2罢了
So that concludes the analysis of the funnel.
这就是漏斗的分析了
We get this crazy running time,
我们得到了这个犀利的运行时间
which is basically sorting bound plus a little bit.
就是排序边界加上了一点
We plug that into our funnel sort, and we get,
我们把它用在漏斗排序里 得到了
magically, optimal cache oblivious sorting just in time.
最优的缓存无关排序 时间刚刚好
Tuesday is the final.
周二就期末考试了
The final is more in the style of quiz one, so not too much creativity,
期末考试的形式跟小测1差不多 没什么新鲜的
mostly mastery of material. It covers everything.
基本包含了所有知识点
You don't have to worry about the details of funnel sort,
你不用复习漏斗排序的具体过程
but everything else.
不过其他的都要看
So it's like quiz one but for the entire class.
就像小测1的豪华增量版
It's three hours long, and good luck.
你们有三个小时 愿算法与你同在
It's been a pleasure having you, all the students.
和你们在一起的时光很开心
I'm sure Charles agrees, so thanks everyone.
我相信查哥也是这么想的 感谢你们所有人
It was a lot of fun.
学算法真™开心啊